Guide to the Cuthbert Simpkins Interviews on John Coltrane, 1971-1974 RL.01194
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cuthbert Simpkins Interviews on John Coltrane
1971-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Simpkins, Cuthbert Ormond, 1947-
RL.01194
3 Linear Feet
Author and medical doctor Cuthbert O. Simpkins (b. 1947) wrote the first biography of jazz saxophonist and composer John Coltrane (1926-1967), titled Coltrane: A Biography (Perth Amboy, NJ: Herndon House Publishers, 1975). The collection contains audio recordings of interviews Simpkins conducted with various family members, friends, and colleagues of Coltrane between 1971-1974 as a part of his research.
65 original audiocassettes (with CD use copies for patron access)
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, Box 1 (containing original audiocassettes) is CLOSED to patron use. CD use copies for all original audio material in the collection are located in Box 2 and are open to patron use.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Cuthbert Simpkins Interviews on John Coltrane were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in December 2008.
Biographical Note
Author and medical doctor Cuthbert O. Simpkins (b. 1947) wrote the first biography of jazz saxophonist and composer John Coltrane (1926-1967), titled Coltrane: A Biography (Perth Amboy, NJ: Herndon House Publishers, 1975). Coltrane was born in Hamlet, N.C., and his family moved to High Point in 1927, where he lived until 1943. Beginning in the mid-1940s, he regularly performed on tenor saxophone as a sideman, including stints in bands led by Jimmy Heath, Dizzy Gillespie, Miles Davis, and Thelonious Monk. By the early 1960s, Coltrane was leading his own ensembles, including an influential quartet with McCoy Tyner, Jimmy Garrison, and Elvin Jones. As a saxophonist, he brought renewed attention to the soprano saxophone in the 1960s, and as a composer and an improviser, Coltrane contributed to a number of harmonic and melodic innovations in jazz.
Collection Overview
The Cuthbert Simpkins Interviews on John Coltrane comprises 65 audio cassettes of interviews conducted by Simpkins between 1971-1974 while researching his 1975 biography of Coltrane. Simpkins interviewed family members, friends, musicians, and other associates from throughout Coltrane's career. The interviews address such topics as: Coltrane's family history, his childhood in North Carolina, the development of his musical style, his influence on other musicians, and his personality. Many also contain personal anecdotes related to Coltrane from throughout his life. The materials include multiple interviews with Calvin Massey, Jimmy Garrison, Larry Young (Khalid Yasin), Ornette Coleman, and others. The audiocassettes have been digitized for patron access, and portions of some interviews have been transcribed, with the transcriptions included in the collection.
Related Material
David Tegnell Interviews on John Coltrane
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jazz musicians -- Interviews; Saxophonists -- United States -- Biography; Jazz -- History and criticism; Jazz musicians; Jazz -- 1951-1960; Jazz -- 1961-1970; Jazz; Jazz -- 1941-1950; Audiocassettes; Compact discs; Tyner, McCoy; Simpkins, Cuthbert Ormond, 1947-; Young, Larry, 1940-1978; Coleman, Ornette; Coltrane, John, 1926-1967; Coltrane, John, 1926-1967 -- Biography; Jones, Elvin; Garrison, Jimmy; Simpkins, Cuthbert Ormond, 1947-; Massey, Cal, 1927-1972
- Audio Recordings of Interviews, 1971-1974, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Interviewee names and interview dates are taken directly from written information on the original cassettes.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  RESTRICTIONS: Box 1, containing original audio cassettes, is CLOSED to patron use. CD use copies are open to patrons and are available in Box 2.
  - Original Audio Cassettes 101-165 (Box 1)
    CLOSED TO PATRON USE
  - CD Use Copies of all Audio Material (Box 2)
    This box contains CD use copies for all original audio material in the collection. Additionally, it contains a folder with more detailed descriptions of the file naming scheme and the relationship between the original media and the digital files. The folder also contains all currently available interview transcriptions, which are noted below.
    - Interview transcripts and information (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Contains partial transcriptions of some of the interviews, noted below. Also contains additional details about the interviews and the file naming scheme.
    - Track 1 - Interview with Pete LaRocca, 16 mins, July 5, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-101A (Box 2, Cd 1)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Dr. James C. Morgan, 7 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-102A (Box 2)
      Partial transcript available in folder.
    - Track 3 - Interview with Walter Hoover, 27 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-102B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Gary Bartz, 15 mins, April 13, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-103A (Box 2, Cd 2)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Gary Bartz, 15 mins, April 13, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-103B (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Steve Kuhn, 46 mins, May 22, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-104A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Ray Draper, 27 mins, May 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-104B1 (Box 2, Cd 3)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Richard Davis, 17 mins, May 22, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-104B2 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Rashied Ali, 15 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-105B (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Rahsaan Roland Kirk, 2 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-106A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Shepard S. Whitted, 15 mins, fall 1972, JAD-2008-0299-107A (Box 2, Cd 4)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Dr. James C. Morgan, 19 mins, fall 1972, JAD-2008-0299-107B1 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Shepard S. Whitted, 11 mins, fall 1972, JAD-2008-0299-107B2 (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Cuthbert Simpkins, 16 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-108A1 (Box 2)
    - Track 5 - Interview with Samuel Burford, 6 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-108A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Samuel Burford, 30 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-108B (Box 2, Cd 5)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Calvin Massey, 22 mins, June 1971, JAD-2008-0299-109A (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Larry Young (Khalid Yasin), 25 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-110A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Odean Pope, 11 mins, June 28, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-111A1 (Box 2, Cd 6)
    - Track 2 - Interview with James Kinzer, 16 mins, June 28, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-111A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with James Kinzer, 22 mins, June 28, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-111B (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Joe Termini, 17 mins, May 14, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-112A1 (Box 2)
    - Track 5 - Interview with Larry Young (Khalid Yasin), 13 mins, May 15, 1971, JAD-2008-0299-112A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 19 mins, May 12, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-112B1 (Box 2, Cd 7)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Joe Termini, 10 mins, May 14, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-112B2 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with James Boyd, 30 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-113B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Mr. Isadore Granoff, 22 mins, Feb. 14, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-114A1 (Box 2, Cd 8)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Mr. Lewis, 4 mins, Feb. 14, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-114A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Mr. Lewis, 13 mins, Feb. 14, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-114B (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Ethel Wilson, 6 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-116B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with John Erskine "Rocky" Boyd, 30 mins, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-117A (Box 2, Cd 9)
    - Track 2 - Interview with John Erskine "Rocky" Boyd, 30 mins, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-117B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 15 mins, Jan. 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-118A (Box 2, Cd 10)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 15 mins, Jan. 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-118B (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Odean Pope, 45 mins, June 28, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-120B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with James Forman, 23 mins, June 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-121A1 (Box 2, Cd 11)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Hank Mobley, 7 mins, June 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-121A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Hank Mobley, 20 mins, June 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-121B1 (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Warren McClinton, 10 mins, June 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-121B2 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Carl Grubbs, 30 mins, Feb. 8, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-122A (Box 2, Cd 12)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Carl Grubbs, 9 mins, Feb. 8, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-122B (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Mal Waldron, 16 mins, Jan. 6, 1974, JAD-2008-0299-123A1 (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Elvin Jones, 10 mins, Jan. 6, 1974, JAD-2008-0299-123A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 5 - Interview with unidentified subject, 5 mins, Jan. 6, 1974, JAD-2008-0299-123A3 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Mal Waldron, 45 mins, Jan. 6, 1974, JAD-2008-0299-123B (Box 2, Cd 13)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 15 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-124A (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 15 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-124B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with George Russell, 5 mins, June 17, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-125A1 (Box 2, Cd 14)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Johnny Coles, 38 mins, June 19, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-125A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Pat Patrick, 30 mins, August 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-126A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Pat Patrick, 23 mins, August 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-126B (Box 2, Cd 15)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Mrs. Hughes (and unidentified interviewees from High Point), 27 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-127A (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Mrs. Dunavant, 29 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-127B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Michael Lawson, 30 mins, July 5, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-128A (Box 2, Cd 16)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Michael Lawson, 25 mins, July 5, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-128B1 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Pete LaRocca, 5 mins, July 5, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-128B2 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Calvin Massey, 30 mins, June 29, 1971, JAD-2008-0299-129A (Box 2, Cd 17)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Calvin Massey, 30 mins, June 29, 1971, JAD-2008-0299-129B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Calvin Massey, 30 mins, June 28, 1971, JAD-2008-0299-130A (Box 2, Cd 18)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Calvin Massey, 23 mins, June 28, 1971, JAD-2008-0299-130B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Gary Bartz (and unidentified associates), 43 mins, June 9, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-131A (Box 2, Cd 19)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Roy Haynes, 40 mins, June 8, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-131B (Box 2, Cd 20)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Gary Bartz (and unidentified associates), 8 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-132A (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Wayne Shorter, 30 mins, July 6, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-133A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Wayne Shorter, 5 mins, July 6, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-133B (Box 2, Cd 21)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Larry Young (Khalid Yasin), 15 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-134A (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Orrin Keepnews, 31 mins, Jan. 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-135A (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Orrin Keepnews, 10 mins, Jan. 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-135B (Box 2)
    - Track 5 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 13 mins, April 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-136A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 13 mins, April 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-136B (Box 2, Cd 22)
    - Track 2 - Interview with McCoy Tyner, 30 mins, Jan. 27, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-137A (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with McCoy Tyner, 6 mins, Jan. 27, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-137B (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with McCoy Tyner, 30 mins, Jan. 27, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-138A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with McCoy Tyner, 30 mins, Jan. 27, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-138B (Box 2, Cd 23)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Zita Carno, 30 mins, July 3, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-139A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Zita Carno, 26 mins, July 3, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-139B (Box 2, Cd 24)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Jimmy Heath, 31 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-140A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Jimmy Heath, 31 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-140B (Box 2, Cd 25)
    - Track 2 - Interview with George "Big George" Russell, 26 mins, Jan. 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-141A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with George "Big George" Russell, 24 mins, Jan. 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-141B (Box 2, Cd 26)
    - Track 2 - Interview with George "Big George" Russell, 26 mins, Jan. 19, 1972., JAD-2008-0299-142A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with George "Big George" Russell, 30 mins, Jan. 19, 1972., JAD-2008-0299-142B (Box 2, Cd 27)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 32 mins, Jan. 6, 1973, JAD-2008-0299-143A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 21 mins, April 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-145A (Box 2, Cd 28)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Jimmy Garrison, 21 mins, April 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-145B (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Rahsaan Roland Kirk (and Ron Burton), 30 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-147A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Rocky Boyd, 14 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-147B (Box 2, Cd 29)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Franklin Brower, 40 mins, July 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-148A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Franklin Brower, 43 mins, July 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-148B (Box 2, Cd 30)
    - Track 2 - Interview with George Braith, 31 mins, April 23, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-149A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with George Braith, 30 mins, April 23, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-149B (Box 2, Cd 31)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Larry Young (Khalid Yasin), 32 mins, April 15, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-150A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Larry Young (Khalid Yasin), 31 mins, April 15, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-150B (Box 2, Cd 32)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Jimmy Oliver, 31 mins, Feb. 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-151A (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Jimmy Oliver, 12 mins, Feb. 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-151B1 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Hasan Abdullah, 9 mins, Feb. 18, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-151B2 (Box 2, Cd 33)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Harold Lovette, 15 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-152A (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Archie Shepp, 4 mins, Jan. 29, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-153A1 (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Rashied Ali, 27 mins, Jan. 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-153A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Rashied Ali, 30 mins, Jan. 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-153B (Box 2, Cd 34)
    - Track 2 - Interview with George Russell, 42 mins, June 17, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-154A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Elvin Jones, 39 mins, June 15, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-154B (Box 2, Cd 35)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Cuthbert Simpkins, 2 mins, June 27, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-155A1 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Pandit Ronu Majumdar, 11 mins, June 27, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-155A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Art Blakey, 21 mins, June 27, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-155A3 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Harold Lovette, 45 mins, June 2, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-155B (Box 2, Cd 36)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Mrs. Ingram, 9 mins, June 28, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-156A1 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Odean Pope, 5 mins, June 28, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-156A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 4 - Interview with Johnny Coles, 11 mins, June 28, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-156A3 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with unidentified subject, 19 mins, June 28, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-156A4 (Box 2, Cd 37)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Jymie Merritt, 17 mins, June 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-156B (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Michael Babatunde Olatunji, 31 mins, May 31, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-157A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Reggie Workman, 35 mins, June 23, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-157B (Box 2, Cd 38)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Ornette Coleman, 42 mins, May 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-158A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Ornette Coleman, 15 mins, May 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-158B (Box 2, Cd 39)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Ornette Coleman, 15 mins, June 1, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-159A1 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Sonny Rollins, 14 mins, June 1, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-159A2 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Reggie Workman, 44 mins, June 23, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-159B (Box 2, Cd 40)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Rashied Ali, 30 mins, Jan. 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-160A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Rashied Ali, 30 mins, Jan. 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-160B (Box 2, Cd 41)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Albert Dailey, 44 mins, May 25, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-161A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Max Roach, 9 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-162A (Box 2, Cd 42)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Art Blakey, 7 mins, June 21, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-162B1 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Sun Ra, 38 mins, June 29, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-162B2 (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Max Roach, 44 mins, June 9, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-163A (Box 2, Cd 43)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Max Roach, 5 mins, June 9, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-163B (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Sun Ra, 27 mins, June 29, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-164A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Sun Ra, 28 mins, June 29, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-164B (Box 2, Cd 44)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Warren McClinton, 30 mins, June 30, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-165A (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Franklin Brower, 45 mins, July 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-115A (Box 2, Cd 45)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Franklin Brower, 19 mins, July 20, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-115B (Box 2)
    - Track 1 - Interview with Ornette Coleman, 20 mins, July 7, 1972, JAD-2008-0299-144A (Box 2, Cd 46)
    - Track 2 - Interview with Thelonious Monk, 8 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-146A1 (Box 2)
    - Track 3 - Interview with Larry Young (Khalid Yasin), 38 mins, no date, JAD-2008-0299-146A2 (Box 2)